Nasr Kasrin (PhD)

LEADER · ENGINEER · 20YRS AI & DATA · ENTREPRENEUR

■ nasr.kasrin@puma.com | 🗥 n42r.github.io | 🛅 nkasrin



With over 20 years of experience in technology innovation, I have led successful initiatives in Al, data architecture, e-commerce, robotics, and more across startups, global corporations, and large-scale R&D projects. Anchored by advanced academic credentials-including a recent PhD in data architecture and management-I blend hands-on expertise with a leadership style centered on exploration, experimentation, and strategic risk-taking. This diverse background enables me to drive business growth and deliver state-of-the-art solutions that elevate user experiences.

Experience

Lead Solutions Architect 2024 - present

PUMA SE, GLOBAL E-COMMERCE ENGINEERING

Herzogenaurach, Germany

- Founded and led an organization of two teams (4+4+2) which improved PUMA.com's performance by 25%.
- Established (+ composed charter) of Ecomm Technical Cats (ETC) organization with a Tech Design Board & innovation forum.
- Led a war-room-like workshop of 15 technical experts to solve a complex problem causing PUMA NA to loose 9/10 orders on product launches.
- Investigated AI/LLMs for supporting software development and devised a initial framework for embedding LLMs in SE.

Co-Founder | CTO | Data Architecture Scientist | Prototyper

2021 - 2024

FREELANCE

Bamberg, Germany

- Co-founding a startup for AI/LLM-driven solutions & building prototypes for products with millions of potential users (left when joining PUMA).
- Developed an Al-driven music recommendation prototype utilizing open-source LLMs, with positive feedback from pilot users (MuzeAI, below).
- · Researched and invented a next-gen data architecture (post-data mesh) for exchanging data across organizations (& awarded a PhD for it).

Research Associate (Team Lead | Dev Lead | Architect | Data Solutions Engineer)

2015 - 2020

University of Bamberg (EU-Funded Manufacturing Project)

Bamberg, Germany

- Led a 4-year project to develop a data management SaaS platform which optimized operational efficiency by 30% in a €3.5 million 8-company EU aerospace manufacturing project (See *github.com/simutool*).
- Engineered a read-heavy SaaS, ensuring seamless operations and future-proof cloud-native architecture (ex., docker, stateless nodes).

R&D Engineer (AI) | Team Lead | Software Architect

2011 - 2014

TAYAIT

Cairo, Egypt

- Built 2 Al players (java, C) for a mobile board game (backgammon), and lead a team of two R&D engineers to port them to Objective-C.
- Led a software engineering team in building 2 iOS mobile apps, driving rankings to 4.5/5 and increasing user engagement by 10.
- Reduced feedback-development cycle times by 25% by coordinating cross-functional collaboration between technical, business, and UI/UX.
- · Saved the company 10-man months by investigating emerging trends and alternative paths and advising the CEO in fruitful directions.

Projects (Titles are hyperlinks)

Guestrrday & MuzeAl

• Developed personal open source projects: a music tagging tool (executed 20.000+ inputs) & an early Al-powered music discovery prototype.

The Basin Network (Doctoral Project)

2019 - 2023

2022 - 2024

• Invented an architectural pattern for data architecture (Cf. data mesh, data lake), culminating in a PhD and publication.

SIMUTOOL Data Lake 2015 - 2019

• Led the design & development of a data management SaaS for a consortium (aerospace, automotive), cutting turnover time by 30%.

Greetings Studio & Tawla (Backgammon Board Game)

2011 - 2014

• Directed two apps (iOS): an E-greeting card creation/sharing app and a mobile game, optimizing user engagement and Elevated app ratings.

Education

PhD. (Dr. rer. nat.)	Faculty of Information Systems & Applied Computer Science, Otto-Friedrich-Universität Bamberg, Germany	2023
Masters of Science	Faculty of Computer Science & Engineering, German University in Cairo, Egypt	2010
Bachelors of Science	Faculty of Computer Science & Engineering, German University in Cairo, Egypt	2009